Today's דף daf is כ"ה chaf hey and we pick up at
the very top of כ"ה עמוד א', chaf hey amud aleph, אמר
ליה רב אדא. amar lei rav adda. So the discussion here after
a fascinating conversation yesterday about כהנים kohanim and לויים levi'im and their
different roles and so on, and I have some answers from some
issues we raised then and I'll mention it at the end of
the שיעור. shiur. Anyway, today we go to another משנה; mishna; we're
dealing again with things which are true for A, not true for
B and vice-versa. So we're talking about how vessels become טמא, tamei,
and a difference between pottery vessels and other vessels. Normal vessels become
טמא tamei because an object that is טמא, tamei, a source of
טומאה, tumah, like a carcass of a dead animal, touches them whether
it touches their outside or their inside, but it's through touch, whereas
a כלי חרס, kli cheres, a pottery vessel, the תורה Torah says
אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו: asher yippol mehem el tocho: when something
falls into its inside, an interior. So for a pottery vessel, the
point is that if the source of טומאה, tumah, let's say a
dead rodent, is in the interior, it makes the vessel טמא tamei
even if it's not touching it, even if it's suspended in air,
but if it touches it without being in the interior, it does
not make it טמא. tamei. Similarly, the way a pottery vessel communicates
טומאה, tumah, passes טומאה tumah on to other objects, is not through
contact but through having something in its interior, and the גמרא Gemara
learned that out even without touching, and the גמרא Gemara learned this
principle out that touching doesn't matter because it says everything in the
vessel becomes טמא, tamei, and if you look at the first three
words of כ"ה עמוד א', chaf hey amud aleph, it says everything
becomes טמא, tamei, ואפילו מלא חרדל, veafilu malei chardal, even if it's
filled with mustard seed. So it means, so if it's filled with
mustard seeds, mustard seed is classically an example of a very infinitesimal
tiny little object. People might know a quote about faith like a
mustard seed, not from our religion. Anyway, so anyway, if it's filled
with mustard seeds, now if it's filled with mustard seeds, if the
טומאה tumah it transmits is through contact, it won't make all the
mustard seeds טמא tamei because only the ones that are touching the
jar, all the other ones that are in the interior of the
jar won't become טמא tamei because they can't transfer that many times.
So if everything becomes טמא, tamei, it must mean the טומאה tumah
is communicated through its presence in the interior, not through contact. So
that's the way כלי חרס kli cheres is different. It has to
do with receiving and transmitting טומאה tumah through presence in the interior
and not through contact like other vessels. So let's continue with this
now, top line of כ"ה עמוד א'. chaf hey amud aleph. Okay,
so אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא, amar lei rav adda
bar ahava le rava, so רב אדא בר אהבה rav adda bar
ahava said to רבא: rava: ויהא כלי חרס מטמא מגבו מקל וחומר.
vehei kli cheres mitamei migabbo me'kal vachomer.
So like the גמרא Gemara has done until now, when the משנה
mishna says that these things are only true for A or only
true for B, it says, well, why don't we just apply them
one to the other from a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Let a
pottery vessel become טמא tamei from its back, backside, meaning without being
in the interior, just through contact based on a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. ומה כל הכלים שאין מיטמאין מאוירן מיטמאין מגבן—all uma kol hakelim
she'ein mitamein me'aviran mitamein migabban normal vessels don't communicate טומאה tumah through
their interior, or actually don't receive טומאה tumah either way through their
interior; they only get it through their back, meaning through contact. כלי
חרס שמיטמא
מאוירו—a kli cheres shemitamei me'aviro pottery vessel that becomes טמא tamei through
something being in its interior, אינו דין שיטמא מגבו—how eino din sheyitamei
migabbo much more so should it be through contact? And, you know,
here, like I said, sometimes these questions are more persuasive and sometimes
they're less; here it is somewhat persuasive because you would think the
idea of receiving and communicating טומאה tumah through being in the interior
is like, you know, contact is the most obvious way you communicate
טומאה tumah through direct touch. Without touching, just presence in the interior,
that you would say is like a stronger ability to communicate and
receive טומאה. tumah. So if it can communicate and receive טומאה tumah
through being in the interior, maybe it should certainly do it through
contact.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר קרא, amar kra, so the verse
teaches: וכל כלי פתוח, vechol kli patuach, any open vessel, אשר אין
צמיד פתיל עליו, asher ein tzamid patil alav, that there is not
a cover that is, like, you know, a tightly fit upon it,
that is bound to it, sealed upon it, טמא הוא, tamei hu,
it shall become טמא. tamei. So this is one of the places,
by the way, that we learn that pottery vessels receive טומאה tumah
only through their interior, that the תורה, Torah, when it talks about
all the vessels in an אוהל המת, ohel hamet, in a house
under a roof where there's a corpse, so the corpse communicates טומאה
tumah right to everything under the roof. But it says if you
have a pottery vessel that has a seal that is tightly fitted
upon it, it does not become טמא. tamei. Now, how does a
seal prevent the pottery vessel from becoming טמא? tamei? Everything under the
roof becomes טמא. tamei. וכל כלי פתוח, vechol kli patuach, I understand
this is understood to mean pottery vessel and we're going to bracket
that for now. Anyway, so how—how does a seal prevent טומאה? tumah?
I mean, if everything under the roof becomes טמא, tamei, how does
a seal prevent it? But if the way the vessel receives the
טומאה tumah is through its interior, then you can say when it
is sealed, the interior is not exposed to this אוהל המת, ohel
hamet, to the, you know, to the—to the room in which the
corpse is, and therefore does not become טמא. tamei. So this clearly
indicates
that
another— Actually, we're going to say that right now.
איזו כלי שטומאתו קודמת לפתחו, eizu kli shetumato kodemet lepitcho, which type
of a כלי kli is it that the impurity comes to its
door? Now this is a little play on words because לקדם לפתח
lekadem lapetach means is like an idiomatic expression which means like, you
know, going out to greet you, like I wake up in the
morning and I come to your house and I knock on your
door to say hello, I come out, you know, I rise up
early to your door, okay, which says so קודם לפתחו kodem lepitcho
here means so on the one hand it means which טומאה tumah
is like eager to enter into a vessel, but also the word
פתח petach here means the opening, meaning which type of a טומאה
tumah is the טומאה tumah that goes through an opening. Where have
we seen vessels that have טומאה tumah coming through an opening and
not just through the exterior? So which one is that true for?
הוי אומר זה כלי חרס, hevei omer zeh kli cheres, that that
is a pottery vessel. Okay, because since we know from an earlier
פסוק posuk that we just quoted yesterday that a pottery vessel communicates
and receives טומאה tumah through its interior, and here's a vessel that
talks about being sealed and by its interior being sealed it's protected
from טומאה, tumah, so it answers Michael's question, we can infer that
we're talking about a pottery vessel. Okay, now how does it tell
us the question we asked? The question we asked is how do
you know a pottery vessel does not also receive טומאה tumah from
its back? Maybe its interior is an addition to normal ways of
receiving טומאה. tumah. So the answer is here because if you have
a pottery vessel in a room with a corpse and the pottery
vessel is sealed tightly, the תורה Torah says that it is טהור,
tahor, it is pure. Well, I understand that the טומאה tumah doesn't
have access to the interior, but it has access to the exterior,
why shouldn't it become טמא tamay like all other vessels? So from
here you see that a pottery vessel only receives טומאה tumah through
its interior and other vessels only receive טומאה tumah through, you know,
contact or do not require the idea of interior.
Well you could still say that if something's actually touching it directly.
You could, but we're assuming here, that's true, you could, but what
we are assuming here is that being present in an אהל מת
ohel mays would be the same as contact. But you're right, you
could make a distinction. It's true. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is not
interested in doing that. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on, וכי
אין צמיד
פתיל עליו? vechi ein tzamid patil alav? Of course.
What, it has nothing to do with the fact that pottery is
porous?
Well, that is a very good question why any of this matters,
you know, what the logic for this distinction is. We, pottery vessels
are given a different status by כשרות kashrus because they are porous
and because they're assumed to absorb taste and not necessarily be able
to remove the taste that's absorbed in it. There is no good
explanation why it should matter for טומאה. tumah. טומאה tumah seems purely
just arbitrary ritual designations. So why should we make a difference between
pottery and non-pottery? The only thing I'll say, which is maybe begging
the question, is that the תורה Torah also says that when a
pottery vessel becomes טמא tamay you cannot purify it, you cannot bring
it to a מקוה. mikvah. Other vessels you can bring to a
מקוה. mikvah. So the consequence of a pottery vessel becoming טמא tamay
is much more severe. So it could be that because of that
the תורה Torah wanted to limit more, right is exactly why we
would read this idea of תוכו tocho as not as an addition
but as an alternative. It wanted to limit the ways in which
pottery vessels could become טמא. tamay. Because then if you have vessels
in your house and somebody dies, right, which would happen then, they
wouldn't take people to the hospital so people would regularly I assume
die at home, right, so you would have to what, break all
your pottery vessels? So no, if they're sealed you're okay. So you
know and there are ways in which, so anytime you basically seal
your pottery vessel you can protect it against טומאה, tumah, right, so
I, that might be a reason, is that, but again it begs
the question so why did the תורה Torah not allow pottery vessels
purification in a מקוה? mikvah? I don't know the answer to that,
but at least that's somewhat of an explanation, yeah.
Did you just define the word seal? You don't mean close, when
you say seal does it mean close in a way that...
I do mean close, it's like there's a lid on it.
Right, and that's it, I
mean it doesn't have to have like a lacquer. It has to
be tightly sealed. Have to break something. No, no, no, no, but
like, I, it's an interesting question I never asked myself about this,
about like what would be if it had the way we do
jars nowadays where it's like very tight but there's
no physical adhesive sealing it. But that might suffice. It does, you
know, so it's some way in which it's tightly sealed. I don't
remember offhand the exact parameters of how to define tightly, okay, but
some way in which it's tightly closed.
But they usually like, you know, plaster it on, don't they?
That's one way, yeah. The question is what is the minimum that
you would need to do? Right, so I'd have to check on
that, okay.
And the question is is that what they were doing all the
time when they were sealing pottery?
I have no idea. Apparently. It doesn't sound like the תורה Torah
you did it as a special way of avoiding טומאה. tumah. It
sounded like this was a normal way of sealing your vessels. So
again one of the explanations might be since you would have to
destroy your vessels if they became טמא tamay it limits the opportunity
for טומאה. tumah. Yes, David.
Maybe another tiny comment on what this implies for the nature of
טומאה. tumah. It doesn't sound like it was just a status. Well,
it sounds like there's some real type of metaphysical reality.
Physical reality. Well, physical.
Yeah, but I mean look. That's an interesting question is how is
טומאה, tum'ah, you know, sort of conceptualized in the תורה? Torah? You
know, is it just, is it some type of a thing that
really travels through air and really gets communicated and contracted and so
on? You know, there's those that certainly understand that, and that these
are really more describing a type of a physics, rather than arbitrary
or, sort of, you know, ritual laws.
How do we understand this גמרא gemara as being something different?
Well, that's what I was trying to say to Bobby, that if,
I mean, although I understand it a little bit begs the question,
but if you start with the assumption that you can't purify pottery
vessels, which, which I mean I understand why should that be true?
But then you could understand that the תורה Torah wanted to more
limit the way in which those vessels become טמא. tamei. So if
it says that contact is not enough, it has to be on
the inside, well you can protect the inside. It's a lot easier
protecting the inside of something than protecting the outside, right? You just
seal it.
It sounds like the second part of the answer.
It sounds like the second part of the answer, what do you
mean?
Like what is טומאה? tum'ah? I mean, is it a physical thing
that as long as you don't get it?
Right, I understand. I understand. I'm just saying that even if it's
purely ritual, you could understand why we might want to make a
distinction here in order to more protect the pottery vessels. But it
begs the question, why can't you, why can't you purify a pottery
vessel? So, you know, you are, I think, you know, the approach
that טומאה tum'ah in the תורה Torah seems to be not just
some, you know, something real and the תורה's Torah more describing how
it gets contracted, you know, there's definitely, you know, there's definitely a
lot of people that take that approach, there's no question.
So what do you make, actually?
Well, if you take the answer that I gave you, right, with
the different approaches being described here is, I'm, one approach is, which
I'm trying to do it in my modern 21st century rationalistic approach,
right, is that these are purely ritualistic laws and we're saying this
law to make it more humane and to not have as big
of a consequence. The other approach, which David is suggesting, is that
no, טומאה tum'ah is actually understood as some real thing that communicates
in the air and somehow it gets absorbed more in pottery or
differently in pottery than it gets absorbed, you know, or contracted to
other vessels. Joe, you wanted to say something? Joe, you wanted to
say something?
I think that טומאה tum'ah is like today we have certain things,
like infections or bacteria.
Right, I think that's what David is saying. That it's the idea
almost like of germs or something. That it's, but it's as if
there's some, something real there, they're present there, right? Look, just to
give you one quick example about that, how this almost these two
approaches get asked in a more conceptual way is a question about,
you know, the principle of, like we're talking now, of anything in
the room of a corpse, of a human corpse, is טמא. tamei.
So there's a question about how do you understand how that operates?
Do you understand or anything that's, you know, that's above a human
corpse, even like, you know, you could be in a plane over
a cemetery or something like that, you know, becomes טמא. tamei. So
how you understand how that operates? So one way of explaining that
is to describe טומאה tum'ah as a thing that is spreading. So
the טומאה tum'ah hits the roof, spreads under the roof, and spreads
to all things in the room. Or in the guy in the
plane over the cemetery, the טומאה tum'ah bursts through the ground, goes
like in a straight up, you know, sort of, you know, pillar
and hits everything above it. That is one, please, that is, that
is, that is one approach. The other approach is to say that,
well, we're not describing טומאה, tum'ah, we're describing the relationship of you
to the corpse. So the, what we're saying is if you're in
the same room with a corpse, you become טמא. tamei. If you
are above a corpse, you become טמא tamei because of your relationship
to the corpse, not because of this thing called טומאה tum'ah that's
spreading. So that almost, you know, the first way very much reflects
an understanding like David, the second way is more reflecting, you know,
the approach I was trying to say to Bobby, which is more
that we're not talking about טומאה tum'ah as a thing, we're just
saying under what circumstances does something become טמא. tamei. So it really,
I think that those are, you know, two very, the two approaches
with טומאה.
tum'ah. Right, when traveling 30,000 feet in the air, it's hard to
say it's like some sort of miasma and germs is going to
spread 30,000 feet in the air. All right, and hard to say
that I have any relationship with somebody 30,000 feet below me.
So there you go. So they're equally, equally, so there's no one
approach which is better than the other, is what you're saying. All
right, so now, all right. What?
They didn't have a, they didn't know that it would be possible
to go that high anyway, once when the laws were formulated. That's
a good point as well.
And one last one is that we have a relationship with השם
Hashem and that's more than...
Okay. All right. So moving on. Okay.
Okay. Shh. Alright let's go on.
Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says, so what do we learn
from this verse? וכי אין צמיד פתיל עליו הוא דטמא v'chi ein
tzamid patil alav hu d'tamei when there is not a top that
is sealed on it, that's when this becomes טמא tamei when it's
in a room with a dead body. הא יש צמיד פתיל עליו
טהור ha yesh tzamid patil alav tahor if there is a top
that is sealed upon it, this vessel is pure. And why doesn't
it become טמא tamei because the back of it is the outside
of it is exposed to this
אהל המת? ohel hameit? So you see that pottery vessels only become
טמא tamei through their interior and not through their exterior. So the
גמרא gemara says fine, so let's try to now argue the קל
וחומר kal vachomer in the reverse. וכל הכלים יטמאו מאוירם מקל וחומר
v'chol hakeilim yitame'u me'aviram mikal vachomer so now let's say all other
vessels shall become טמא tamei from their interior based on a קל
וחומר kal vachomer from pottery. ומה כלי חרס שאין מיטמא מגבו umah
kli cheres she'ein mitamei migabo and just as a pottery vessel, which
is not made טמא tamei from its... pottery vessels do not become
do not receive טומאה tumah from their exterior. They only receive טומאה
tumah from their interior as we've
described, כל הכלים שמיטמאי מגבן, Kol ha-kelim she-mitammei migaban, so all other
vessels that do receive טומאה tumah from their
exterior, אינו דין שמיטמאי מאוירן, eino din she-mitammei mei-aviran, and how much
more so should they also get it from their interior? Now you're
telling me receiving טומאה tumah from your interior is a weaker form
or a different form, so let's make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
So if you get it from your exterior, how much more from
your interior? So how do you know that they that these are
mutually exclusive?
So, אמר קרא, amar kera, the verse says תוכו, tocho, its interior.
When something falls in its interior, and that's the verse that's explicitly
talking about a pottery vessel. תוכו של זה, Tocho shel zeh, the
its interior of this one, of a pottery vessel, ולא תוכו של
אחר, ve-lo tocho shel acher, not of any other type of a
vessel. So therefore because of the ו, vav, תוכו, tocho, its interior
means only for pottery vessels and this is how we know that
they're mutually exclusive. Just to clarify by the way, because although the
גמרא Gemara and I said this at the beginning is contrasting interior
and exterior, it's a little imprecise. Other vessels, if something touches their
interior, also become טמא. tamei. The real point is through touch or
through presence in the interior. But the גמרא Gemara is sort of
simplifying that as exterior versus interior. But not to get confused, a
normal vessel if something touches the inside, it is טמא, tamei, but
that's because it's about touch. It's not about presence in the interior.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to say one minute,
והני תוכו הדרשינהו? ve-hanei tocho ha-darshinehu? We use תוכו tocho to tell
you other things. How can you use it to tell you only
the pottery vessel and not and not other vessels? So the גמרא
Gemara says ארבע תוכו כתיבי. arba tocho ketivei. It says תוכו tocho
four times. It really says it two times but we can get
four דרשות derashot out of it. How? It says תוכו tocho and
תוך. toch. It could have said אל תוך, el toch, to the
interior. It says תוכו, tocho, its interior. So that allows us a
special דרשה. derashah. Now it didn't even have to say תוך. toch.
It could have said, I think תוספות Tosafot points out what could
it have said, it could have said,
oh,
it could have said בו, bo, אשר יפול מהם בו, asher yipol
meihem bo, into it. So just the use of words of תוך,
toch, interior, is itself seen as an extra word that allows us
a דרשה. derashah. So תוכו, tocho, תוך, תוכו, toch tocho? תוך. toch,
So it says the word תוך toch. twice in those פסוקים pesukim
that are talking about pottery vessels receiving and communicating טומאה tumah and
that gives us four דרשות. derashot. חד לגופיה, Chad l'gufiei, one just
for to tell you פשט, peshat, like something falling inside of it.
Okay, וחד לגזירה שוה, ve-chad l'gezeirah shavah, one is a גזירה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. What's the גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah? The גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah tells you as we this is what we said yesterday, the
same way it communicates טומאה tumah to everything inside of it like
this thing filled with mustard seed, all the mustard seeds become טמא,
tamei, it communicates טומאה, tumah, it also receives טומאה tumah from its
interior. So if the dead rodent is suspended in the interior, it
becomes טמא. tamei. So both it receives and communicates. So the way
we say both, because the תורה's Torah talking about communicating טומאה, tumah,
the way we know it's also about receiving is the גזירה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. So that's how we use number two. חד לגזירה שוה,
Chad l'gezeirah shavah, וחד תוכו של זה ולא תוכו של אחר. ve-chad
tocho shel zeh ve-lo tocho shel acher. One is what we just
explained, its interior and not the interior of other vessels, non-pottery vessels
like metal vessels or wood vessels. וחד, Ve-chad, and here's a fourth
point which is telling us something new that we did not know
yet, תוכו ולא תוך תוכו. tocho ve-lo toch tocho. Its interior and
not the interior of its interior. ואפילו כלי שטף, Ve-afilu kli shetef,
and even washed vessels. Now why are they called washed vessels? Basically
כלי שטף kli shetef is the way to describe anything, thank you,
is the way to describe anything that is non-pottery. Why? Because non-pottery
vessels can be purified in a מקוה. mikvah. So שטף shetef which
refers to the idea of washing or rinsing evokes the idea of
a מקוה mikvah which means all other vessels that are non-pottery that
you can put in a מקוה mikvah that have different ways of
also becoming טמא. tamei. So what does this last thing mean? What
it means is the following: let's say you've got one vessel, right?
Let's say you've got a big vessel here and you've got your
rodent in it and it's a pottery vessel, and inside that box,
like it's sort of like what do they call those Chinese boxes
or something, right? You have a smaller box in that other thing,
and that smaller box is where you've got, you know, like a
food that you don't want to become טמא. tamei. So the question
is, what does it mean to be in the vessel? The vessel
is טמא, tamei, but this thing, it's in a vessel in a
vessel. Which vessel is it considered to be in?
Is it covered?
Well, no, it's not covered. But the way it I wish I
had a more visual thing here, but the way it operates is
we're talking specifically that the interior box, the walls of it go
higher than the exterior box. So when something is in the interior
box, is it also considered to be in the exterior box? And
the answer here we learn from this verse is no. It is
only considered to be in the interior, it's not considered to be
in the exterior box because the walls of the interior go higher.
And
this has two implications. So for example, let's say you've got your
dead rodent in the interior box. The exterior box, well, I'd say
box here, but I'm talking about... The exterior pottery vessel is טהור
tahor because it's not like the rodent is not considered to be
in the pottery vessel. It's considered to be in the interior box,
right, not in the larger vessel. Or the flip. Let's say the
pottery vessel is טמא. tamei. Okay, the outer one, the bigger one,
and you've got food or other stuff in your interior. That remains
טהור tahor because it is considered to be not in the outer
one, it's considered only to be in the inner one. So the
inner one has higher walls, right? If it has lower walls it's
obviously considered fully contained, but if it has higher walls, it's considered
to only be what's in the interior is considered to be only
in the interior, not in the exterior. And that works whether it's
receiving or transmitting טומאה. tumah. Now this idea, where is something, is
an idea that comes up in a lot of different areas of,
you know, if it's in one place which is in thing A
which is in thing B, which thing is it in? Like a
great example the גמרא Gemara has about this is a question about,
you know, if you have a vessel, the question the גמרא Gemara
asks is whether כליו של לוקח kailav shel lokeach are
מקנה ברשות מוכר. makne b'reshut mocher. If you put something in my
vessel, right, I'm buying something from you, then I purchase it because
it's in my vessel. It's like I'm in possession of it, it's
in my thing. Let's say my vessel is not in my hand.
Let's say my vessel is on your front yard and you put
the thing you're selling me, the flour whatever, into my vessel. Do
I acquire it because it's in my vessel or no, it's not
really in my vessel, it's really in your yard? Right? So where
is the thing? It's in my vessel which is in your yard,
what's its like primary location?
And the גמרא Gemara asks like these types of questions in a
number of different ways. One vessel in another, you know, how do
you view it, right?
So if something is so this is one example of that and
for the issues of כלי חרס kli cheres we say that if
the inner one is taller than the outer one, they're considered then
anything in the inner is not in the outer. Now, a question
that רש״י Rashi asks is of course, well, you know, why doesn't
the inner vessel become טמא tamei as well, right? Because and once
the inner vessel becomes טמא, tamei, let's say my outer vessel is
טמא, tamei, why doesn't the inner one become טמא? tamei? And once
the inner one is טמא, tamei, shouldn't have the ability to prevent
the stuff inside of it from becoming טמא? tamei? So רש״י, Rashi,
you know, רש״י Rashi has an answer to that basically because basically
because what?
That's what the לימוד limud is, specifically.
No, well that's not what רש״י Rashi says. רש״י Rashi says because
pottery vessels only communicate טומאה tumah to foods, they don't communicate טומאה
tumah to vessels that are inside of them. So that's what רש״י
Rashi says. So the vessel, the inner vessel itself, does not become
טמא tamei and again that allows for it to be considered its
independent thing and to protect, as it were, what's inside of it
either from becoming טמא tamei or from communicating its טומאה tumah outside.
Okay, so that's what we learn from this final point of תוך
ולא תוך תוכו, toch v'lo toch tocho, not the interior of the
interior. If it has one vessel inside another then that's considered to
be a separate location. Okay, so that's what we know from this.
So let me make sure I understand this. So if the walls
are lower in the interior vessel, then no matter which way you
slice it everything becomes. Correct. Correct. Okay, so now רש״י Rashi though,
what is this תוך תוכו? toch tocho, I mean if you're saying
that רש״י Rashi is saying.
It's still an interior. There's two separate questions. One is, is the
vessel טמא? tamei? Even if it's not טמא, tamei, but the food
that's in vessel A that's in vessel B should be considered in
vessel B. Why because it's in vessel A should it not be
considered in vessel B? That's what it teaches you, it's not. Okay,
if the walls are lower it's considered to be in vessel B,
but if the walls are higher, even though A is in B,
what's in A is not considered to be in B.
What if you put your hand in a טמא tamei vessel?
Then well, yes, that wouldn't happen because you are a person can
only become a ראשון. rishon. And once a vessel receives טומאה, tumah,
so the vessel itself is a ראשון, rishon, so a vessel can
only make things into a שני. sheni. So a vessel can really
only communicate טומאה tumah to like food objects, it can't communicate טומאה
tumah to other things.
To your hand.
Right. Because it can't communicate טומאה tumah to a person. Even if
you were able to go fully into a vessel, it was a
huge vessel, you wouldn't be טמא tamei because a vessel
can only make things, a
vessel is a ראשון, rishon, it can only make things a שני.
sheni. The only thing that can become a שני sheni is food.
Then what do you need the לימוד limud for?
Again, it's not to tell you the inner vessel is טהור. tahor.
It's to tell you what's in the inner vessel is only considered
to be in the inner vessel not the outer one.
So yes,
the inner vessel is טהור, tahor, that wasn't our question. Our question
was, is the food in the inner vessel טהור?
tahor? When they say תוך toch תוכו, tocho, they mean the food
and not the vessel itself. Right. Can a
decaying thing or something that used to be living make somebody טמא?
tamei?
With the exception of people, as a general rule, yes, but with
the exceptions of certain states that happen to people, like menstrual flow,
seminal emission, צרעת, tzara'at, you know, those types of things, a person
becomes
טמא, tamei, although
but, you know, but no, that's the thing. But in terms of
an object that communicates טומאה, tumah, yes, that starts, that's basically something
that used to be alive.
Like a biological thing. Yes, right.
Well, for many people the. concept of טומאה, tumah, the primary concept
of טומאה tumah has to do with death, you know, that's for
a lot of people, so even issues like
biological function,
what, and biological function, right, but often a biological function associated with
like death or disease. That's at least one approach to understanding טומאה.
tumah. Right, so the right, so, so
the birth explanation, what's the birth explanation? Is it the right, that's
obviously the obvious question to the whole thing about a woman and
childbirth, I'm trying to remember נדה Niddah for example is easier because
נדה Niddah is potential life. That's right. Giving birth, yeah, yeah, whether,
you know, is that might be associated might be tried to be
associated with also the fact that the, I'm not sure that the,
I'm trying to remember how that fits into the model. I'd have
to that's the obvious one that people ask. It might be the,
either it is that it's not just death, it's also life in
any sort of powerful life force whether life or death. It might
also be that birth is, you know, the idea obviously that a
woman is, you know, it's sort of like it's a type of,
you know, woman's light, you know, it's very risky in terms certainly
in the olden days or whatever, you know, in terms of, you
know, women could die in childbirth. So it could fit into the
sort of the illness model, not to say that childbirth is an
illness, but you know.
Now the life is so momentary, so to that extent maybe.
Maybe. I have to see how it fits into the death and
illness model. Yes. Right, or it could be the blood that's associated
with it. Correct, correct, yes.
Was it a profound and overwhelming change in biological status that makes
that changes thing from.
Right, that's interesting. Right.
A בעל קרי's baal keri not a profound overwhelming change.
I thought it was. I mean I mean maybe the idea is
something that you can't fully control that changes you from one biological
state to another. I mean there might have been some issue around
that.
That's interesting. Yeah.
Because it really only applies to potentially living things or things that
happen to living people. It doesn't happen just it's not like the
magical fairy dust thing.
It's about people really or it's just about
animals or people right.
But that doesn't I don't think that goes back to David's question
because yes that's the source of it, but then what happens as
a result? Is what happens as a result because it's so powerful,
you know, that it created this type of thing in the air
or was it because of this, you know, more like.
A capacity for something living to interact with something intangible.
Right, right. Okay, very good. All right, so now let's just wrap
this up. We're already we're already halfway through today's שיעור. shiur. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, oh, so we did תוכו
תוכו. tocho tocho.
So where were we? ולא יטמא
תוכו תוכו ולא יהיו כל הכלים מטמאים מגבן אלא מתוכן ובנגיעה. V'lo
yitamei tocho tocho v'lo yehu kol hakelim mitamim migaban ela mitochan u'v'negiya.
So גמרא Gemara says okay now let's try to say though, you
know, normally we've been doing with either status A or status B,
maybe you need both A and B. Maybe a normal vessel which
is needs both to be touch both both criteria of interior and
the criteria of touch, criterion. So maybe a normal vessel only receives
טומאה tumah both through touch and the interior, touching the interior, מקל
וחומר mi'kal v'chomer and we'll make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Right,
so we already know that a pottery vessel is only through its
interior, and the idea of interior doesn't work by a standalone by
other vessels. So it says okay maybe it doesn't work by a
standalone by other vessels but maybe it works in conjunction with the
idea of touching from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. ומה כלי חרס
שמטמא מאוירו אין מטמא מגבו, U'ma kli cheres shemitamei me'aviro ein mitamei
migabo,
pottery vessel is the interior and not the exterior, כל הכלים שאין
מטמאים
מאוירן, kol hakelim she'ein mitamim me'aviran, all other vessels that do not
receive טומאה tumah from their interior, אינו דין שאין מטמאים מגבן, eino
din she'ein mitamim migaban, so they should be like pottery vessels, you
know, if they if they can't even get interior טומאה tumah they
surely shouldn't get טומאה tumah from exterior from contact and maybe their
only interior טומאה tumah is through the combination of the two, touch
of the interior. So אמר קרא amar kra so the verse says
no. וכל כלי פתוח אשר אין צמיד פתיל עליו טמא הוא, V'chol
kli patuach asher ein tzamid patil alav tamei hu, we said this
before, open vessels that are not do not are not sealed in
the the house of a dead body are טמא, tamei, which means
that if they are sealed they're טהור. tahor. So it says הוא
טמא הוא, hu tameihu, האי הוא דכי אין צמיד פתיל עליו טמא
הא יש צמיד פתיל עליו טהור, hai hu de'chi ein tzamid patil
alav tamei ha yesh tzamid patil alav tahor,
the pottery vessel is something that without a cover it's טמא tamei
with a cover it's טהור. tahor. The pottery vessel is something that
a cover protects it. הכל הכלים Hakol hakelim between שיש צמיד פתיל
עליהם בין שאין צמיד פתיל עליהם bein she'yesh tzamid patil aleihem bein
she'ein tzamid patil aleihem
whether they do or don't have a cover מטמאים mitamim become טמא
tamei in the house of a corpse. So again the understanding is
we learned this idea of mutually exclusive from the fact that the
תורה Torah says exposed pottery vessels, only exposed pottery vessels become טמא
tamei in the house of a corpse, meaning covered not. So there
we learned that pottery vessels only receive טומאה tumah from their interior
not exterior, and we also learned that the תורה Torah saying this
is only true by pottery vessels, all other vessels in the house
of a corpse do become טמא tamei regardless of if they're sealed.
So from this we learned that all other vessels has nothing to
do with their interior, can receive טומאה tumah even from their exterior.
Okay, so that wraps it up. That's how we know those two
things are mutually exclusive. exclusive. We go on now, I just somebody
once pointed out to me, you know it's only, it's only people
that learn גמרא Gemara that regularly use the word vessels. When you're
a normal when you're a normal life would you ever use the
word vessels? Okay anyway, moving on. Vessel? Yes, pot, pots, pans, plates.
I need a vessel here.
All right anyway, what? All right so moving on let's-
people
use it for boats.
Boats?
Oh, okay there you go.
All right anyway. All right, let's next משנה. Mishna. טהור בכלי עץ,
Tahor b'khlei etz, we're not out of vessels yet. Those things that
are pure for wood vessels, טמא בכלי מתכות tamei b'khlei matakhot are
impure for metal vessels. טהור בכלי מתכות, Tahor b'khlei matakhot, those that
are pure for metal, טמא בכלי עץ tamei b'khlei etz are pure
for wood, which means not pure, not pure. Before we were talking
about how do they receive or transmit טומאה, tumah, here we're talking
about what state of completion,
what constitutes a vessel. And the difference is the following: wood vessels,
the גמרא Gemara learns from a פסוק pasuk that says כל כלי
עץ או בגד או עור או שק, kol kli etz o beged
o or o sak, any wood vessel or a sack, and it
says the same way a sack is something that you put stuff
in, has an interior, again interior, has a receptacle, I should more
say, a wood vessel can only be susceptible to receive טומאה—this tumah
is not the act of receiving טומאה, tumah, but can have the
potential of becoming טמא—if tamei it has a receptacle. So if you've
got a spoon, for example. But if you had a wood fork,
okay, although I don't know forks have a little bit of a
curve, so that might be different, but imagine you just had like
a wood knife, it would not become טמא. tamei. Although it's a
totally functional vessel, it's not- it can't become טמא. tamei. Not only
that, there's even a question about a wood table. So there it
might become because a table you can actually, it can, you know,
it will contain something put on it, although it's not shaped as
a receptacle. So there there's a question about rabbinic טומאה tumah and
so on. But basically, wood things need a receptacle. Metal does not
require a receptacle. But what we're going to find out is metal
does require that it be finished, it be completely finished off, you
know, the whole working of it and and the finishing touches were
all done. So that's what the משנה Mishna is saying: by wood
what matters is receptacle; by metal what matters is finishing touches. And
something could be receptacle without finishing touches or finishing touches without receptacle,
and then it and then it would only be טמא tamei for
one category.
And you can ruin dyes on your wooden knife.
Correct, correct. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, our Rabbis taught. גמרא. Gemara. גולמי
כלי עץ, Golemi klei etz, so here's the word גולם, golem, right?
What's a גולם? golem? A גולם golem is right, exactly, an unfinished
product, right? That's the whole idea of you know where the whole
idea of a גולם golem comes from is you take this big
lump of clay and you give it life. So גולם golem means
an unfinished product. So you have some type of an unfinished wood
wood vessel. טמאים, Temei'im, it's טמא tamei as long as it has
a receptacle. פשוטיהן, Peshuteihen, but if the wood vessel is flat with
non-receptacle like a knife, טהורים, Tehorim, they're טהור. tahor. So for wood
what matters is that it has a receptacle, regardless of whether it's
fully finished or not. גולמי כלי מתכות, Golemi klei matakhot, however, unfinished
metal vessels, טהורים, Tehorim, are טהור. tahor. If it's unfinished, it's not-
does not receive טומאה. tumah. פשוטיהן, Peshuteihen, their flat metal vessels like
a knife, טמאים Temei'im are טמא. tamei. נמצא, Nimtza, so from this
you
learn: טהור בכלי עץ טמא בכלי מתכות, Tahor b'khlei etz tamei b'khlei
matakhot, טהור בכלי מתכות טמא בכלי עץ. Tahor b'khlei matakhot tamei b'khlei
etz. That what's pure for one is impure for the other and
vice versa. Here means able to receive טומאה. tumah. ואלו הן גולמי
כלי עץ. V'ele hen golemi klei etz. Now it's going to give
you some descriptions. Here is what is considered to be unfinished wood
vessels. כל שעתיד לשוף, Kol she-atid lashuf, something that has yet to
be, to be like polished. לשבץ, Leshabetz, רש"י Rashi says לשבץ leshabetz
means like to put in certain type of a filigree, certain types
of engravings, you know, something that makes it look nice and aesthetic.
לגרר, Legarer, to scrape, like you know like you sand it down.
לקרכב, Lekarkev, which רש"י Rashi says means also like this is also
some type of engraving, not exactly clear to me how it's different
than לשבץ. leshabetz. לקרכב, Lekarkev, right exactly. שובץ Shabetz might be more
like adding something, some type of thing on it, and קרכב karkev
might be carving something in it. להטיח בטונס, Lehatiach betunas, or to,
again, to smooth it with some type of a- רש"י Rashi says
that this might be that this is a fish oil or fish
skin that you would smear on a vessel to maybe seal it
or to, you know, to give it a gloss or something. מחוסר
כן, Mechusar kan, let's say it doesn't have a base. You have
your nice wood vessel but you know you have your which can
operate but it does not- you haven't created a base, which is
interesting. Let's say for example you have a cup, right? So you've
got your cup and you want to attach it to a base,
you know, with like a קידוש Kiddush cup, right? With like the
the stem and the whatever, but you haven't, but it can still
function as a cup, it just it doesn't have the base attached.
או אוגן, O ogen, or it doesn't have an ear. So you
have let's say like a colander, you know, or some type of
a- of a bowl and you normally would have handles. You didn't
put on the handles yet. Okay. אוזן, Ozen, I'm sorry, אוגן, ogen,
excuse me. אוזן Ozen is the handles, אוגן ogen is like a
lip. Okay, a lip or handles, all those things, it's totally functional.
It's just not totally finished. In all those cases, טמא, tamei, it
does become טמא. tamei. However, מחוסר חטיטה, mechusar chatita, if it lacks
carving out, if it lacks the being the receptacle being made, then
טהור, tahor, because it's about here having a receptacle, not about being
finished. Now the גמרא Gemara says, מחוסר חטיטה פשיטא. mechusar chatita peshita.
If it's lacking carving out, of course we know that if it
doesn't have a receptacle. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, לא צריכה
דחק כפיזה בכבא. lo tzericha dechaka kafiza bekava. You are planning on
making it with a deep receptacle that can contain a כב, kav,
which is a large measure, and you've only carved out a smaller
receptacle so far. So it does have a receptacle, but the receptacle
aspect of it is not finished. Your intention is to make it
a deep, a deep container, and it's a shallow container. So yes,
intention does matter, being unfinished does matter in the case of unfinished
receptacle. So although it has a receptacle, if it's unfinished, it's not
yet טהור. tahor. But any other aspect being unfinished, it is functional
and it is, can become טמא. tamei. Now תוספות Tosafot points out,
one minute, תוספות Tosafot points out that there's another גמרא Gemara which
says that if you don't sort of sand it, it is טהור,
tahor, it's not, and תוספות Tosafot has a nice distinction. If you
take a look at this little תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
להטיח בטוניס, lehatiah betunis, this last little תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
היפשרו מנין טמא, hipsharu minei tamei, בפרק שני דסנהדרין אמר, beperek sheni
deSanhedrin amar, כלי עץ מאימתי מקבלין טומאה, kli etz me'eimatai mekablin tumah,
העריסה והמיטה, ha'arisa vehamitah,
so a kneading trough and a bed, משישופם בעור הדג, misheyishufam be'or
hadag, when you smooth them over with the fish skins. And here
it says that even if it's not smoothed with the fish skin,
it's טהור—no, tahor it's טמא. tamei. So what's the difference?
ותרץ דשפה דהתם היינו להסיר הקסמים הגדולים שמזיקין לישב עליה. vetereitz deshafa
dehatam hainu lehasir taksamim hagedolim shemazikin leyashev aleiha. There you're talking about
removing the big splinters that if you don't remove the big splinters,
how do you use a vessel? You're going to get splinters in
your hand. אבל שפה דהכא אינו אלא לנוי בעלמא להחליקו ולצחצחו. aval
shafa dehacha eino ela lenoy be'alma lehachliko letzachtzacho. That's just to make
it look smoother and nicer. So actually a certain degree of unfinishing
like you'll get splinters if you use it, that would not yet
be considered a usable vessel. But once it's usable and the only
thing lacking is the finishing touches, for wood that's fine because the
emphasis is the receptacle. Now that is in contrast to the metal.
So let's look at metal. ואלו הן גולמי כלי מתכות, ve'elu hen
gomei klei matachot, these are metal vessels that are unfinished that are
טהור, tahor, כל שעתיד לשוף לשבץ, kol she'atid lashuf leshabet, anything that
in the end you're going to, you're going to like a polish,
to add a filigree, לגרר לחרכב, legarer lecharkev, to scrape, לחרכב lecharkev
or לחרכב lecharkev maybe, again to, to scrape, to engrave, להקיש בקורנס,
lehakish bekurnas, to give the final hammer blow. For שבת Shabbat the
idea of מכה בפטיש, makeh bepatish, the final hammer blow, is a
important concept in שבת Shabbat and it refers to the finishing touches
that you do to an object. So the metal is a little
bumpy, you haven't done the final hammer blow to finally smooth it
out. מחוסר קן או אוגן או אוזן, mechusar kan o ogen o
ozen, it's missing a base or a lip or a handle, an
ear, טהור. tahor. In all those cases it is pure because by
metal it is not about receptacle, it's about being finished. מחוסר כיסוי,
mechusar kisuy, if it just doesn't have a cover, טמא, tamei, then
that doesn't matter, then it can become טמא tamei because the cover
is considered a separate object, it's not considered part of it. So
now the גמרא Gemara finally says the question, it's quite fascinating here,
the גמרא Gemara is actually going to ask what is the logic.
Until now we've tried to supply the logic. By yesterday's talks about
a whole difference between כהנים Kohanim and לויים, Levi'im, today we talked
about a whole difference between pottery and non-pottery. Here the גמרא—but Gemara
it wasn't in the גמרא—here Gemara the גמרא Gemara asks, so let's
take a look. מאי שנא הני ומאי שנא הני? mai shna hani
u'mai shna hani? How is one different than the other? Why does
metal go by, you know, polished, by finished, and wood go by
receptacle? So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי יוחנן אמר הואיל ולכבוד עשויין.
Rabbi Yochanan amar ho'il u'lechavod asuyin. Because metal vessels are done for
like, you know, they're used in more respectable contexts, and they're, you
know, you bring out your metal vessels to honor your guest. Okay,
you bring out your cheap wood vessels if, you know, you're eating
at home, so you're home, you use your paper products and your
disposable products, you know, you have nice company and you bring out
the metal vessels. Okay, so metal vessels, so what does that mean?
It means that since they are made for, the normal context in
which they're used is to show respect to the people that you're
using them with or, you know, people that have respectable positions use
metal vessels. They don't use wood vessels. So the vessel has to
be in a respectable state. It has to be finished. If it's
not finished, then it's not really considered to be fit with its
use in the society. Wood vessels are very basic and fundamental, so,
you know, everybody uses them, who cares if they're finished or not?
They're, you know, they're common people vessels. So there, finished is not
important, here finished is important.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, רב
נחמן אמר הוו דמי יקרים. Rav Nachman amar hovu de'damei yakarim. Because
they're expensive. Which is not the context in which they're used but
because they cost more and you're paying more money for them, you
expect them, you don't want to pay good money for For something
that's unfinished. So מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what where would there be
a case where it would have one quality and not the other?
איכא בינייהו כלי עצם, ika beinaihu k'lei etzem, bone vessels. Bone vessels
presumably were expensive, but not necessarily used, you know, limited to being
used in cases of respect and honor and so on. So therefore,
if the if so how do we categorize bone vessels? Are they
like metal or they like wood? Right? If if the issue is
because they're expensive they have to be finished, so they would be
like metal. If the issue is that because they're used as ways
in ways of respect, you know, in those types of contexts, wood
bone vessels are used by average people and in an and normal
context and therefore they would not have to be finished. And the
גמרא Gemara says ואזל רב נחמן לטעמיה, ve'azal Rav Nachman leta'amei, רב
נחמן Rav Nachman goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב נחמן כלי
עצם ככלי מתכות דמו, de'amar Rav Nachman k'klei matachot damu, that bone
vessels are like metal vessels and they they go by being finished.
So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל, miklal, that implies כלי עצם מקבלי
טומאה, klei etzem mekablei tumah, that they that they
that they become טמא tamei biblically here it means, because you're see
it seems like your discussion is not at a rabbinic level but
at a biblical level. אין, in, yes, דתניא רבי ישמעאל בנו של
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר מה תלמוד לומר, detanya Rabi Yishmael beno
shel Rabi Yochanan ben Beroka omer mah talmud lomar, what does the
verse mean when it says וכל מעשה עזים תתחטאו, vechol ma'aseh izim
titchata'u, all acts
all things made out of goats you shall purify, meaning that they
can become טמא tamei so you need to purify them. So what
does it mean everything made of goat, not just limited to goat
hair? להביא דבר הבא מן העזים, lehavi davar haba min ha'izim, even
things that come from other parts of the goat, מן הקרניים, min
hakarnayim, from the horns, ומן הטלפיים, umin hatalpayim, from the hooves, that
meaning even things that we we would call bone vessels can become
טמא. tamei. שאר בהמה וחיה מנין, shear behemah vechayah minayin, how do
you know about other animals? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches
וכל מעשה, vechol ma'aseh, all things done. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר
עזים, im ken mah talmud lomar izim, so why does it mention
goats? פרט לעופות, perat le'ofot, that if you make something out of
bird bones, those would not become טמא tamei presumably those are too
whatever fragile or not significant, only things made out of animal bones,
you know, or hooves or horns etc. become טמא. tamei. So here
is the distinction and again what's interesting is, you know, well what's
not explained I should start by saying is, why would vessels need
a receptacle? Why would vessels don't just go by the fact that
they become functional? And you can't say well it's too hard to
describe what functionality means, because we say that by metal vessels, right?
By metal vessels we say that as long you know anything that
is functional is considered a vessel as long as it's done. But
it might be that that's exactly the flip, that if you're describing
that it's complete, so you're emphasizing a person's intention, right? How they
planning on using it, you know, and therefore you could say that
that's what defines vessel is that you're planning on using it in
a certain way and you're complete and you've made it in a
certain way and you've completed it. A wood vessel once you don't
describe that the process is complete, we're really bracketing a lot your
intentionality. If we're bracketing your intentionality, how do we describe whether something
is a vessel or not? I'll give you an example, a toothpick,
is that a vessel? You can use it for something, right? Well
how's it different, so a toothpick is a vessel? How about a
splinter? How about a little how about a little piece of wood
I find out in the forest? I could also use it as
a toothpick. Right, so if you're not, so if if you were
focusing on functional on on the process of making and intention then
you could say well if I am carving out a toothpick, that's
a vessel, right? But that you're focusing on my process. Whereas by
but but the wood vessel does not focus on process, it doesn't
say the process is done. So if it's not focusing on process,
it focuses on its objective functionality, so there we might say that
to have a receptacle makes something considered to be objectively functional. Whereas
by metal vessels where we focus on process and we say it's
done, so we don't have to maybe define functionality. We can just
say you've been working to make this a vessel and you have
finished the process. So that's maybe a way of explaining the difference.
I mean what I'm trying to get at is the גמרא Gemara
only explains why metal vessels require being finished and wood not. Because
metal are more expensive, they're used in more sort of like, you
know, context of giving honor, so therefore unfinished is a problem. What
it doesn't explain is why does the idea of receptacle why is
that central to a concept of vessel by wood and not by
metal? So what I'm suggesting is that when well because it helps
you define something objectively as a vessel. Because how do you define
what what you know what a vessel means, right? Like I said,
is a toothpick, is that a vessel or not a vessel, right?
I mean how do you define when something is a vessel? Having
a receptacle helps in terms of the objective definition. And maybe that's
more important by wood where we're not focusing on the process and
intentionality as we do by metal. So that's just again something to
help understand the other half of the equation, not why not why
metal requires finishing but why wood requires having a receptacle. You had
a question Bobby?
No? Only problem was with your מעשה. maiseh.
What? Well again, but the point is that if you you know
what are we going to do, describe a million legitimate functions that
objectively make something a vessel? Right, and let's say I've come up
with a back scratcher and I've come up you know there's a
million things you can invent that would be a... a function of
something that decides it as a vessel. So you can't come up
with a full list to do it objectively. So one thing that
you could say objectively makes maybe defines something as a vessel is
that it's a receptacle.
Okay, so everything is complete?
What? Right, so that's my point. So you could say complete, which
focuses on the process and the intentionality and that's what we say
by metal, or you could say it's objectively usable as a vessel.
But what type of functions are you going to pick? So we
pick a central function, having a receptacle. All right, so again.
But you said if it's a receptacle and it's not finished.
Right, so we don't totally bracket intentionality. That is true. It doesn't
explain everything. I was wondering if somebody was going to bring that
up. All right, let's take a look at... Yes?
Why don't
we just use the word manufacture?
Well, that's because that is a good point. Normally we assume that
vessels are manufactured. The גמרא Gemara does talk about finding some natural
object that's usable. What?
Coconut.
Coconut, right.
And right, and then, but it doesn't automatically become a vessel. There
it requires like intention to use it as such. I think the
idea that כלי, keli, again this word vessel, very much is suggest
part of the connotation of that word is that it is something
that is like a human artifact, right? That is something that is,
the idea of a... it's not something that I can use as
a cup, but it is a cup, suggests something that is like
part of human society, made, manufactured, intention, and so on. So I
think actually the חידוש chiddush is when the גמרא Gemara says that
even if something is natural and hasn't been manufactured, it can become
a vessel if you intend to use it as such. But I
do think that the basic sense of human
control and definition is central to this idea. Okay, so let's take
a look now at the next case.
Totally shifting categories. החייב בשקדים המרין פטור במתוקין, החייב במתוקין פטור במרין.
Hachayav bishkedim hamarin patur bimetukin, hachayav bimetukin patur bamarin. It's like we
did, we did קדשים, Kodshim, and then we did טומאה וטהרה, Tuma
veTahara, now we're into like זרעים. Zeraim. So we say that you
have these types of nuts that are, if they're bitter, a certain
species of them are bitter, but they're really bitter when they are
fully mature. When they are small nuts, they actually are edible. Then
you have normal nuts which are not edible when they are immature,
but they are edible when they're fully developed. So again, when is
something considered to be food and obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'ma'asrot
and so on? So it depends. Those things what are obligated, החייב
בשקדים המרין, hachayav bishkedim hamarin, bitter nuts, which means the only things
obligated there are the immature ones because only then are they edible.
פטור במתוקין, Patur bimetukin, you are exempt from תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'ma'asrot
by the sweet, normal nuts, because those when they're immature are not
normally fit for being eaten. And the reverse: החייב במתוקין, hachayav bimetukin,
when you're obligated in the sweet when they're mature, פטור במרין, patur
bamarin, you're exempt for in the bitter nuts because those are not
edible when they are mature.
Is that connected in any way to before?
Yes, well, you see you just came in, but for the last
week what we've been doing is a משנה Mishna started by talking
about the way you do
שחיטה shechitah from the front would not be good for a טריפה,
treifah, the breaking of the neck, sorry מליקה, melikah, for the slaughtering
of birds, in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and the way you
do מליקה melikah would not be good, from the back, is not
a legitimate place to do שחיטה shechitah from. So that got into
these what's good for A is not good for B, what's good
for B is not good for A. And now we're taking a
little tour of all areas of ש"ס. Shas. So we did, right,
we did קדשים, Kodshim, we did טהרות, Taharot, and now
we're in זרעים.
Zeraim. It's actually interesting. I haven't checked, but we might go through
all ששה סדרים, shisha sedarim, okay? We now have done three of
the סדרים: sedarim: קדשים, Kodshim, טהרות, Taharot, and זרעים. Zeraim. Okay, so
okay, so let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. שקדים המרין
קטנים חייבין, Shkedim hamarin ktanim chayavin, bitter nuts, the small ones are
obligated. גדולים פטורין, Gdolim pturin, the big ones, meaning mature ones, are
exempt because that's when they're bitter. מתוקין, Metukin, the normal sweet nuts,
גדולים חייבין, gdolim chayavin, mature ones are obligated, קטנים פטורין, ktanim pturin,
the immature ones are exempt from תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot. רבי ישמעאל
ברבי יוסי אומר משום אביו, Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yossi omer mishum aviv,
so Rabbi Yishmael says in the name of his father, זה וזה
לפטור, zeh vezeh liphtur, both are exempt. ואמרי זה וזה לחיוב, ve'amri
zeh vezeh lachiyuv, both are obligated. So what does it mean both
are exempt? So I'll read a תוספות Tosafot what he says. He
says both forms of the bitter nuts are exempt. Well, that makes
a lot of sense, because if they're immature, they're also exempt because
they are, because even though they're edible, they're not yet considered a
developed fruit. So it might be subjectively edible, but as a... objectively
it's not yet a developed fruit. And the big ones are obviously
exempt. So that makes sense. But some say he obligates both. So
how could you obligate both? אמר רבי אילא הורה רבי חנינא בציפורי
כדברי האומר זה וזה לפטור. Amar Rabbi Ila horeh Rabbi Chanina beTzippori
kedivrei ha'omer zeh vezeh liphtur. So Rabbi Chanina ruled that both are
exempt. And now the גמרא Gemara says, ולמאן דאמר זה וזה לחיוב,
גדולים למאי חזו, ul'man de'amar zeh vezeh lachiyuv, gdolim l'mai chazu, how
can you use the big bitter nuts, the mature bitter nuts? אמר
רבי יוחנן הואיל ויכול למתקן על ידי האור, Amar Rabbi Yochanan ho'il
veyakhol l'matkan al yedei ha'or, because you can make them edible by
cooking them. So even though in this stage as raw they're not
edible, since they could become edible by processing, they are considered to
be food and obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot. Okay, let's just
read the next משנה. Mishna. How can you use the big bitter
nuts, the mature bitter nuts? So אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan,
מאי חזי? mai chazi? הראוי למתקן על ידי האור, ha-ra'ui l'matkan al
yedei ha-ur, because you can make them edible by cooking them. So
even though in this stage as raw they're not edible, since they
could become edible by processing, they are considered to be food and
obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. trumot u'ma'asrot. Okay, let's just read the next
משנה mishna and we'll end with that. התמד. ha-temed. Now תמד temed
is the making of wine by adding water to lees. Lees is
the gook at the bottom of whatever, right, when you press grapes.
So obviously you want to get out some of the juices that
are left in the grapes, you don't want anything to go to
waste, so you fill the barrel with water and the juices go
into the water and therefore you get like a weaker type of
a wine and that's what this תמד temed is. Okay, so this
תמד temed עד שלא החמיץ ad shelo hechmit before it's fermented. So
the idea is that is it considered water or is it considered
wine? The משנה mishna assumes that it matters if it gets a
little of this grape juice in it. So the משנה mishna assumes
that when it ferments it's finally considered wine. Until that point, it's
considered water. Okay, so התמד, ha-temed, this type of whatever,
water-juice, water-grape-juice, עד שלא החמיץ ad shelo hechmit before it's fermented, so
it's considered water, אינו ניקח בכסף מעשר, eino nikach b'kesef ma'aser, you
can't buy it with מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. You can only
buy food products, I mean like fruit products, not water. You can't
buy water with מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. It has to be
something that is considered like a type of a fruit or a
type of an animal, right? So you cannot buy this yet because
it's not yet grape juice or wine. ופוסל את המקוה. u-posel et
ha-mikvah. And if it went into a מקוה mikvah as drawn water,
drawn water that's added to מקוה mikvah water before it has the
full amount, ארבעים סאה, arba'im se'ah, invalidates the מקוה. mikvah. Okay, once
it has the full amount it doesn't, which is why once in
all standard מקואות mikva'ot you have a בור bor of ארבעים סאה
arba'im se'ah which nobody ever goes into and that connects to all
the other בורות borot which you're constantly taking out the water and
refilling it and cleaning the water and so on, so people could
go into a clean מקוה. mikvah. But the only reason that's good
is because there's a בור bor pit of, separate place of ארבעים
סאה arba'im se'ah which is the full amount which never gets, never
goes down. But if it went below ארבעים סאה arba'im se'ah and
drawn water was added to it then it would invalidate. So this
at this stage if it was added to a מקוה mikvah in
that circumstance it would invalidate. This is still considered to be water.
If you added wine it would not invalidate. Only drawn water invalidates,
grape juice does not invalidate. Exactly. Can it add to? There's some
things that don't invalidate but don't add to the amount and other
things that neither invalidate nor add to the amount. Okay.
Do you know what? We are very, well we're very pampered nowadays
because we're all so מפונק, mifunak, you know, we have different standards
of
cleanliness, right? Okay. משהחמיץ mishe-hechmit from the time it ferments ניקח בכסף
מעשר ואינו פוסל את המקוה. nikach b'kesef ma'aser v'eino posel et ha-mikvah.
Then you can buy it with מעשר ma'aser money, it's considered wine
and if added to a מקוה mikvah does not invalidate it. האחים
השותפים. ha-achim ha-shutfim. Now here's a totally different. So that was זרעים.
zra'im. Now we are
on basically going into like דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, נזיקין. nezikin. So
here you have brothers that are partners. Now brothers partners means they
equally inherited a father's estate. So actually this is quite interesting because
you know normally הלכה halacha does not have a concept of corporation.
It has a concept of partnership. You and I can be in
a partnership but it doesn't exist as its own, but that's like
half mine half yours. It doesn't exist as its own entity as
a corporation and that makes a lot of challenges nowadays dealing with
the question about what is the halachic status of corporations. The closest
analogy that הלכה halacha has to the idea of corporation is when
people equally inherit an estate. Because then it's not considered like we're
partners, then it's considered like the estate exists as its own entity
and we are owners of the estate but it's not partners of
our separate things brought together, the estate is its own entity. So
here at once, so here brothers who are partners because they are
האחים השותפים ha-achim ha-shutfim כשהחייבין בלבון keshe-chayavin b'kalbon פטורים ממעשר. p'turim mi-ma'aser.
So if they are partners because they have divided the estate and
then they have re-entered into a partnership, so it's a partnership not
a corporation, then they have to pay a קלבון. kalbon. קלבון kalbon
is when they give their half-shekel every year, you add a little
bit because for the money changer, I won't go into it but
anyway for the money changer to break a full shekel into a
half-shekel. So each one is giving a half-shekel. So are they considered
to be giving one shekel as one entity or one shekel as
two entities? So and when they're giving it as two entities they
have to pay this קלבון kalbon which is the fee to the
money changer. So when they are חייב בלבון chayav b'kalbon meaning they
are considered two entities because they divided the estate and then re-entered
into a partnership, so they are considered to be two entities that
are just in partnership, so that's why they pay the money changer
fee, פטורים ממעשר. p'turim mi-ma'aser. Then when their animals give birth they
don't have to give every tenth animal as מעשר, ma'aser, מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser behemah, because you only give that when you are individually own
the flock, not when you own it in partnership.
כשהחייבין במעשר בהמה, keshe-chayavin b'ma'aser behemah, the flip, when they do give
מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah which means what? It's not a partnership, it
is the estate, they have not divided the estate, so it's considered
to be one entity. So if you're one entity, one entity giving
one shekel, you don't have to pay the... money changer's fee because
you're not supposed to be giving two half שקלים, shekels, you're only
supposed to be giving one שקל. shekel. So therefore פטור מן הקלבון.
patur min hakalbon. You're exempt from the money changer's fee. So it's
a question, is it one half שקל shekel or one full שקל,
shekel, רשי Rashi tries to work that out. We're going to bracket
that for now. But again what is really interesting about this is
the idea of being one entity and not a partnership is very
relevant for us for corporations and the closest analogy you have here
is inheriting an estate. One final word to tell you about the
issues that were raised yesterday which I looked up, which I checked,
about the לוים Leviim and the כהנים, Kohanim, both רשי Rashi and
the רמבם, Rambam, although I did not find it explicit in the
גמרא, Gemara, assume that the 24 group rotation that they had for
the, for going up to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so for
the כהנים, Kohanim, that the משנה Mishnah in תענית Taanis which I
mentioned to you that says the לוים Leviim also on a rotation,
it wasn't just a rotation to be present in the קרבן korban
that was also their rotation of service. So that the לוים Leviim
were equally divided into 24 groups and like the כהנים Kohanim and
each group only worked, roughly two weeks a year and of that
they were subdivided into days, so really just like the כהנים, Kohanim,
any individual לוי Levi really pretty much worked only two days a
year, right? He would go to ירושלים Yerushalayim the week that was
his week which was one out of 24 and he would only
work in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash his one day out of
that week. So that's in terms of that issue about the לוים
Leviim and the other point is the question that we said yesterday
when a לוי's Levi voice is no longer good, he can't serve,
does that mean that he can't serve at all or only that
he can't sing? So the רמבם Rambam actually says יראה לי, yeiraeh
li, which is an interesting phrase in the רמבם Rambam when he
says that I can't find a source for it, but this is
what I he says the רמבם Rambam says יראה לי yeiraeh li
that a לוי Levi with a bad whose voice has cracked because
of old age or infirmity or whatever can still do the other
work, can still be the gatekeepers in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
which goes to the point we said yesterday but the לוים Leviim
it's very much about their service, their job, their role, so even
if they can't do one role they're still valid for the other
role. So just want to get back to
this סוגיא sugya comes next.